And here we are in Google Colab, ready for fun with models.
구글 콜랩에 왔습니다 모델들과 즐길 준비가 됐죠
So first we do the usual Pip installs and some imports.
먼저 Pip 설치와 수입 작업을 할 거예요
Now this will take a little bit longer for you because I have cheated and run this already right before
이건 좀 더 오래 걸릴 거예요 이걸 녹음하기 전에 이미 비트를 써서
recording this so that it can be a bit faster.
실행했거든요 좀 더 빠르게요
The Pip installs will probably take 30s to a minute to to all go through for you.
피프를 설치하는 데 30-1분이 걸릴 거예요
So once we've done the Pip installs, we sign in to hugging face.
피프 설치가 끝나면 얼굴 포옹으로 로그인해요
I think you're used to this now.
이제 익숙해진 것 같네요
Hopefully you've got the token set up as your secret on the left.
왼쪽에 비밀이 담긴 토큰이 있으면 좋겠네요
Um, and I'm now going to set some constants for the names of the models we'll be playing with in the
이제 상수를 설정하겠습니다 포옹 페이스 허브에서 함께 플레이할 모델들의 이름에
Hugging Face hub.
대해서요
As always, it's company slash, the name of the model or the model repo.
늘 그렇듯 모델명 또는 모델 회수 회사명이죠
So we're going to be playing with llama with Phi three with Gemma two.
3번과 피 2번과 라마와 놀 거예요
And then I'm leaving an exercise for you to repeat with quanto the mighty LLM from Alibaba Cloud.
연습 문제를 낼 테니 콴토와 함께 반복하세요 알리바바 클라우드의 위대한 LLM이죠
And then I've also given Mistral here.
미스트랄도 여기 있어요
Now, I have to say, this is probably going to be a model that will be too big unless you've splashed
이건 너무 큰 모델이 될 수도 있어요 큰 GPU에 돈을 쏟아붓지
out on on some big GPUs.
않는다면요
Uh, in which case the the ask for you is to go to Huggingface hub and find a nice model that's 8 billion
그럴 경우 H깅페이스 허브에 가서 80억 매개 변수가 넘는 모델을 찾아서
parameters or fewer and, uh, use that instead.
그걸 대신 사용하세요
Pick the one you like or one that's that's popular or is is doing well at the moment and see what you
마음에 드는 걸 고르거나 아니면 지금 인기가 있거나 잘 팔리는 걸 골라서 어떻게 해석할지
make of that.
보세요
But do be sure to have completed at least five models.
하지만 적어도 5개는 완성해야 해요
So with that, let's set those constants, and then let's make a messages list in a format that we know
이제 상수를 설정하고 메시지 목록을 만들게요 이 시점에서 우리가 잘 아는 형식으로요
so well at this point, with a system message and a user message as two dicts in a list.
시스템 메시지와 사용자 메시지죠 목록의 2개 독점으로요
No more explanation needed for that.
더 설명할 필요 없어요
So you remember from last time that you need to, uh, agree to the, um, llama 3.1 terms of service
지난번에 라마 3에 동의해야 했던 거 기억하죠? 한 가지 서비스 조건은 모델 페이지에서
by going to the model page and um, pressing the agree.
동의를 얻는 거예요
If you haven't already done that, um, then please do so so that you have access to llama 3.1 model.
아직 안 하셨다면 llama 3에 액세스할 수 있도록 하세요 모델은 하나예요
Now this is something new.
이런 건 처음 봐요
I want to talk a bit about something called quantization, which I mentioned.
제가 언급했던 퀀타이즈라는 것에 대해 잠깐 얘기할게요 비트
So quantization is a rather surprising thing.
퀀타이즈는 놀라운 개념이에요
Uh, the idea is that we can say, look, we, we want to load in this model into memory, but when
이 모델의 경우 메모리에 로드하고 싶은데 그렇게 할 때
we do so we want to reduce the precision of the numbers of the weights that make up the model.
모델을 구성하는 무게의 정밀도를 줄이는 거죠
These weights are normally 32 bit floats.
이 무게추들은 보통 32비트 플로트예요
Uh, 32 bit floating point numbers make up the weights in this deep neural network.
32 비트 부양점 숫자는 이 심층 신경망의 무게예요
What if we brought them in with fewer bits?
덜 채워서 가져오면 어떨까요?
Uh, so 32 bits, of course, is four bytes.
32비트는 4바이트로 계산할 수 있고요
Um, and, uh, we might want to try and cram, uh, more of our, of our numbers into less memory.
그리고 숫자를 더 적어 넣는 게 좋을 것 같아요 less 메모리에요
Um, and that process of reducing the precision so that you have more coarse numbers in your model is
정밀도를 줄이는 이 과정을 퀀타이즈라고 합니다 모델에 거친 숫자가 더 많이
known as quantization.
보이게 하는 거죠
And that's something that we're going to do.
그게 우리가 할 일이죠
And I remember being very surprised when I first heard about this, that the, uh, initially people
이 이야기를 처음 들었을 때 정말 놀랐던 기억이 납니다 처음에는
talked about taking your 32 bit numbers and replacing them with eight bit numbers, much, much lower
32 비트 숫자를 8 비트 숫자로 대체하면 정확도가 훨씬 떨어진다고들 했거든요
And the thinking was that, surprisingly, whilst of course the accuracy decreases a bit, it doesn't
그 비트는 놀랍게도 정확도는 조금 떨어지지만 생각만큼 떨어지진
decrease as much as you might think.
않아요
It doesn't decrease, it doesn't become four times worse.
줄어들지도 않고 4배로 악화되지도 않아요
Uh, it just becomes a bit worse, uh, and tolerably so and worth the trade off in terms of more memory.
좀 더 나빠지지만 견딜 만해요 메모리가 더 많다면 비트를 걸 만하죠
I was surprised to hear that, and I was even more surprised to hear that you could do more than that.
그 말을 듣고 놀랐지만 그보다 더 많은 걸 할 수 있다는 걸 알고 더 놀랐어요
You can actually reduce it, not down to eight bits, but all the way down to four bits.
8비트가 아니라 4비트로 졸일 수 있어요
That's half a byte if you're counting.
0.5 바이트예요 세어본다면요
You can reduce from 32 bit number down to four bits going into the number.
32비트 숫자를 4비트로 줄일 수 있어요
And again accuracy sure is is is is hurt, but not by as much as you might expect.
다시 말하지만 정확도는 손상됐지만 기대만큼 크진 않아요
Not I would have expected it would be profoundly different.
완전히 다를 줄은 몰랐어요
And it's not it's quite tolerable.
견딜 만해요
And it allows for much bigger models to fit into memory and load faster and run faster and so on.
훨씬 더 큰 모델이 메모리에 맞아 더 빨리 로드되고 더 빨리 달리게 해주죠
So this is something that people do a lot quantization.
사람들이 많이 하는 거죠
It's a powerful tool, uh, particularly when you get to training and you're having to do lots more
강력한 도구예요 특히 훈련을 받거나 이런 모델로 많은 작업을 해야 할 때는요 get
work with these models.
it get it
Uh, quantization is a lifesaver.
퀀타이즈는 구세주예요
You may remember I mentioned that at some point in a few weeks time, we're going to get to a technique
기억하실지 모르겠지만 몇 주 후에 큐 로라라는 기술을 배울
called Q Laura, a way of fine tuning in an efficient way.
거예요 효율적으로 미세 조정하는 방법이죠
And in Q, Laura, the Q of Q, Laura stands for quantization.
Q의 로라, Q의 로라는 퀀타이즈를 뜻하죠
So it is something we will be coming back to from time to time.
그래서 이따금 다시 보게 될 거예요
So in the meantime we are using a library called Bits and Bytes, which goes hand in hand with the hugging
그동안 비트 앤 바이트라는 라이브러리를 사용합니다 포옹하는 트랜스포머 라이브러리와 밀접한
face Transformers library.
관련이 있죠
It's a wonderful library and you can create a new bits and bytes config object to that will be using
훌륭한 라이브러리예요 새 bits와 바이트 구성 객체를 만들 수 있죠 우리가 원하는
shortly to describe what kind of quantization we want to do.
수량화가 뭔지 곧 설명드릴게요
And we are going to say load in four bit equals true.
로드 인 for 비트 = true라고 하죠
We're going to go all the way down to four bits.
50센트까지 쭉 내릴 거예요
You can also here say load in eight bit equals true.
로드 인 8 비트 = true도 할 수 있어요
Instead if you want to do eight bits and maybe you want to try doing both and see if you can tell the
대신 8bit를 하고 싶다면 둘 다 해서 차이를 확인할
difference in accuracy.
수 있죠
And now this again is very surprising.
이것도 정말 놀랍죠
But you also can do four bit use double quant equals true.
근데 4비트 퀀트 = True도 할 수 있어요
And this means that it quantizes all of the weights, not not once, but twice.
한 번도 아니고 두 번씩 모든 무게를 수량화한다는 뜻이죠
Uh, saving a little bit more memory.
메모리를 좀 더 저장하려고요 비트
And the results of doing this again doesn't massively impact the accuracy of the results.
이걸 다시 한다고 해서 결과의 정확성에 큰 영향을 주진 않아요
So it's a good trade to make and people do it.
좋은 거래고 사람들이 그렇게 해요
Um, this is this is saying that in doing the calculations use a this this data type A, B 16, which
이 데이터 형식 A와 B 16을 이용해 계산을 한다는 뜻입니다
makes, uh, makes a some improvement in performance.
그러면 성능이 향상되죠
So this is quite common as well.
이것도 꽤 흔한 일이에요
Uh, and then this is about the so when you have reduced the numbers down to four bits, how how will
여기서 중요한 건 숫자를 4비트로 줄였을 때 4비트 숫자를 어떻게
how to interpret how to treat that, that those four bit numbers, how to compress it down to four bits.
처리하고 압축하는지에 관한 거죠
And this, uh, NF four is a four bit representation of numbers.
이 NF4는 4비트로 숫자를 나타내요
The N stands for normalized.
평범화됐다는 뜻이죠
And I understand that it's to do with with considering these numbers to follow a normal distribution
이런 숫자들을 고려하는 것과 관련 있다는 걸 압니다 일반적인
allows for more more accuracy when you're compressing things down to just four bits.
분포를 따르려면 4비트로 압축할 때 더 정확할 수 있죠
So, um, these these two are probably less important.
이 둘은 less로 보여요
They're not expected to make a massive difference.
큰 변화를 기대하진 않아요
They're meant to be.
둘은 운명이에요
It's meant to be.
운명인 거죠
Good settings to have, though.
설정이 좋네요
And this one makes some difference.
이건 좀 달라요
And this one makes a huge amount of difference in terms of memory.
이건 메모리 면에서 큰 차이를 만들어요
And none of it is too bad in terms of the output.
결과물 면에서는 나쁘지 않아요
So with all of that chit chat, we've now created our quant config, our bits and bytes config.
이 모든 대화로 우린 이제 퀀트 구성, 비트 및 바이트 구성을 만들었어요
This is something we're familiar with.
이건 우리에게 익숙한 거예요
We are going to create a tokenizer for Lama.
라마에게 토큰을 만들어 주려고요
This line is a new one that I haven't talked about before.
이 대사는 처음 언급하는 거예요
Uh, the uh, there is something called a pad token, which is which token is used to fill up the prompt
패드 토큰이라는 것도 있는데요 신경망에 추가할 것이 있을 때 프롬프트를
if there needs to be more added to the prompt when it's fed into the neural network.
채우는 데 쓰이는 토큰이죠
Uh, and the, um, it's a sort of common practice to set that pad token to be the same as the special
일반적인 관행으로 패드 토큰을 문장 끝, 프롬프트 토큰의 마지막과
token for the end of sentence, the end of the prompt token.
동일하게 설정하는 것이죠
Uh, and if you don't do this, you get a warning.
Get을 안 하면 경고를 받아요
It doesn't matter that you get a warning.
Get you 경고는 중요하지 않아요
I don't think it makes any impact.
효과가 없는 것 같아요
But if you don't want to get the warning, then you keep it in here and you see that people have this
경고를 받고 싶지 않다면 get을 선택하세요.
in as very standard in, in a lot of code that you'll see.
많은 코드에서 사람들이 표준으로 사용하는 것을 볼 수 있어요.
Okay.
네
And so then we are going to use our tokenizer.
이제 토큰라이저를 사용할 거예요
We're going to call the apply chat template function that you know.
채팅 템플릿 적용 함수라고 부를게요
Well that takes our messages as a list of dictionaries and converts it into tokens.
그건 우리 메시지를 사전 목록으로 받아들여 토큰으로 변환하는 거죠
And there we are pushing that onto our GPU.
그걸 GPU 위에 적용했어요
So let's run that and the tokenizer will get to work.
get을 실행하면 토큰izer가 작동할 거예요
And what we're going to do next is load our model.
다음으로 할 일은 모델을 로드하는 거예요
So what does this line do.
이 선은 뭐죠?
So first of all it's very analogous to this line.
우선 이 대사와 아주 유사해요
Here we created a tokenizer by saying auto tokenizer dot frompretrained.
여기서 토큰라이저를 만들었는데 오토 토큰라이저. FROMpretrep이라고 입력했어요
We create a model by saying auto model for causal LLM from pre-trained.
미리 배운 자동 LLM을 위한 모델을 생성하죠
Now this is the general class for creating any LLM.
LLM을 생성하는 일반 클래스죠
A causal LLM is the same as an autoregressive LLM.
인과적 LLM은 자가적 공격 LLM과 같아요
And that means it's an LLM which takes some set of tokens in the past and predicts future tokens.
LLM은 과거의 토큰을 가지고 미래의 토큰을 예측하는 것이죠
And basically all the llms we've talked about have been that kind of LLM.
기본적으로 우리가 얘기한 모든 llm은 그런 종류의 LLM이었죠
Later in the course, we will look at one other kind of LLM, which has some some use from time to time.
과정 후반부에 다른 종류의 LLM을 살펴보겠습니다 때때로 사용되는 거죠
But for everything that we're talking about for this sort of generative AI use case, we'll be working
하지만 우리가 말하는 이런 생성적인 인공지능 사용 사례에선 인과적 llms 즉
with causal llms or autoregressive llms.
자동적 위반 llms를 연구할 거예요
And this will be the way to create them from pre-trained we pass in.
미리 훈련된 걸 이용해서 만드는 거죠
Just as with the tokenizer, we pass in the name of the model.
토큰이처럼 모델 이름을 전달하는 거죠
We tell it that if we have a GPU, we want to use that GPU.
GPU가 있다면 그걸 사용하고 싶다고 하죠
That's what Device map auto does.
그게 Device Map 오토의 역할이죠
And we pass in the quantization config, the quant config that we just set up and that is how we build
그런 다음 퀀트화 구성에서 넘깁니다 방금 설정한 퀀트 구성요 그게 모델을 구축하는 방법이죠
The model is the real code, which is actually our large language model as software, as Python code,
모델은 실제 코드입니다 즉, 소프트웨어로서의 큰 언어 모델로서 파이썬 코드로서 우리가
which we're going to be able to run.
실행할 것이죠
And under the covers it is PyTorch.
그 아래는 피토치예요
It is a series of PyTorch layers, layers of a neural network that will be able to feed in inputs and
파이토치 층으로 구성돼 있어요 신경망 층으로 구성되어 있어서 입력값에 입력하면 출력이
get out outputs.
나오죠
So it's the real deal.
진짜 물건이네요
Now, it will probably take longer when you run this because I just ran it, and so it didn't have to
이걸 실행하면 시간이 더 걸릴 거예요 방금 실행했으니까요 완전히 새로운
do as much work as if it was a completely fresh box.
상자처럼 많은 작업을 할 필요가 없었죠
What actually happens when when you run this is it downloads.
이걸 실행하면 실제로 발생하는 일은 다운로드예요
It connects to hugging face.
얼굴을 안는 것과 연결되죠
It downloads all of the model weights from the Hugging face hub, and it puts it locally on the disk
Hub에서 모델 무게를 다운로드해 Google Colab 인스턴스의
of this Google Colab instance in a cache in a special file, which is a temporary file on the desk of
디스크에 로컬로 놓습니다 이 박스의 데스크에 있는 임시 파일 캐시에요 나중에 이 박스와 연결을
this box, which will get deleted when we later disconnect from this box so that this model is now temporarily
끊으면 삭제됩니다 이 모델은 이제 일시적으로 디스크의 박스에 저장됩니다 메모리에
stored on the box on disk, and it's also loaded into memory as well, ready for us to use.
로드되기도 해서 우리가 사용할 수 있게 되죠
We can we can ask the model how much memory it uses up by calling get memory footprint.
모델에게 물어볼 수 있어요 get 메모리풋프린트를 호출해 메모리를 얼마나 사용하는지요
And so we will see what that says.
뭐라고 하는지 보죠
It says the memory footprint of this model is about 5.5GB.
이 모델의 메모리 공간은 약 5개라고 나오네요 5기가바요
And so if we look at the resources for this box, you can see that we are using about 5.5GB of space
이 박스에 대한 리소스를 보면 약 5개를 사용하는 걸 보실 수 있어요 상자는 5GB로 하고요
And it's bouncing around in the past because I've been running this already.
이미 실행하고 있었기 때문에 과거에도 흔들리고 있어요
But you can imagine that when you look at it, you'll be starting from down here and it will bump up
하지만 자세히 보면 이 아래부터 시작해서 5.5cm까지
to about five and a half.
올라갈 거예요
And on the disk, we're using up plenty of space because it's been loaded into the cache of the disk.
디스크에서 많은 공간을 사용하고 있습니다 디스크 캐시에 로드되어 있기 때문이죠
Okay.
네
Almost ready for for for prime time here.
황금 시간대 준비가 거의 다 됐어요
At first we're going to look at the model itself.
먼저 모델 자체를 살펴보죠
And we do that simply by printing the model.
모델을 프린트함으로써 그렇게 하죠
What comes up when we print the model is a description of the actual deep neural network that is represented
모델을 프린트하면 이 모델 객체에 의해 표현되는 실제 심층 신경망에 대한 설명이
by this model object.
나와요
This is what we're looking at here.
여기 보이는 게 그거예요
It's real layers of code representing the layers of the deep neural network.
딥 신경망 층을 나타내는 코드 층이에요
And these are all this is showing PyTorch classes that have set up that are being that are that are
이건 전부 PyTorch 클래스를 보여줍니다 모델에 의해 참조되는
referenced by model.
설정이죠
Uh, and again, this is a practical class with only a touch of theory from time to time.
다시 말씀드리지만 실습 시간이라 가끔 이론만 살짝 다룰 거예요
But it is worth looking at this, depending on your level of of knowledge of the innards of deep neural
하지만 깊은 신경망과 그 층의 내장에 대한 지식 수준에 따라 살펴볼
networks and the layers.
가치가 있어요
Some of this may be super familiar to you.
익숙한 내용도 있을 거예요
You may be comfortable seeing that it begins with an embedding layer, which is how the tokens become
토큰을 심는 레이어에서 시작한다는 게 익숙하실 겁니다 토큰을 신경망에
embedded into the neural network.
심는 방법이죠
And you can imagine that this dimension, these are showing the dimensions and it's the dimensionality
이걸 상상해 보세요 단어의 입체성을 나타내는
of the vocab.
거예요
Uh, and you'll then see that there's a series of modules, each of the layers in the neural network.
그리고 모듈이 여러 개 있는 게 보이시죠 신경망의 각 레이어예요
There are attention layers that you'd be expecting to see, particularly as you know that attention
예상했던 대로 주의 깊게 보는 층이 있어요 특히 주의 깊게 보는 게 가장 중요하잖아요
As the paper said, attention is all you need, and that is at the heart of what makes a transformer
종이에 쓰여 있듯이 주의만 기울이면 돼요 이런 주의 층이 트랜스포머를
a transformer, these attention layers.
트랜스포머로 만드는 핵심이죠
And then we have multi-layer perceptron layers right here.
그리고 다중 페르셉트론 층이 여기 있어요
And there is an activation function.
활성화 함수가 있어요
Uh, again, as those those who are more familiar with the theory will be expecting to see this.
이 이론에 더 익숙한 사람들은 이걸 보길 기대하겠죠
The activation function that is used by this llama 3.1 model is the ReLU activation function, which
이 llama 3이 사용하는 활성화 함수죠 1번 모델은 리루 활성화 함수로
is the sigmoid uh, linear unit, which is described in Pytorch's documentation right here.
구형 아니 선형 유닛으로 여기 문서화에 나와 있죠
Uh, and it is also known apparently as the swish function.
스위시 함수라고도 알려져 있죠
Uh, and it's, it's basically x times the logistic sigmoid of x.
기본적으로 물적 X의 X 곱하기 X죠
And that's what the activation function looks like.
활성화 함수는 이렇게 생겼어요
Again, if you're into the theory of deep neural networks, you know exactly what this is.
심층 신경망 이론에 관심이 있다면 이게 뭔지 정확히 알 거예요
If you're not, then then don't worry.
아니라면 걱정하지 마세요
Just get a general sense of what's happening here, and it's something that you can look more at as
여기서 무슨 일이 일어나는지 전반적으로 파악하세요 이 모델이나 나중에 다른 걸 연구할
you study this model and others afterwards.
때 더 자세히 살펴볼 수 있는 거죠 Get it
At the end of that, there's a, uh, like a, some, some, uh, uh, layer norm layers and then the
그 끝에는 표준 층이 있고 그 끝에는 직선
linear layer at the end.
층이 있어요
So this is worth looking at particularly, uh, depending on your level of knowledge of, uh, PyTorch
이건 특별히 살펴볼 가치가 있어요 피터치 신경망에 대한 지식이
neural networks.
있다면요
But also later when you look at other models, you could do the same thing.
나중에 다른 모델도 똑같이 할 수 있어요
Look at the model's output.
모델 출력을 보세요
Look, look at the model, print the model, look at what it looks like and compare with lama3.
모델을 보고 인쇄해서 어떻게 생겼는지 보고 라마3와 비교해요
I'm going to break for the next video, but in the next video, we're then going to run this and then
다음 비디오에선 쉬도록 하죠 다음 비디오에선 이걸 실행하고 다른 모델도
run the other models too.
실행할 거예요
So don't go anywhere.
그러니 어디 가지 마세요
See you in a second.
이따 봐요